As I watched her do this, for the first time in my life, I had a priceless feeling: that I could be of some use to this world. That feeling was very special, because I am not meant to be useful.
Alors que je la regardais faire, pour la première fois de ma vie, j'ai eu le sentiment inestimable que je pouvais être utile à ce monde. Ce sentiment était très spécial parce que je ne suis pas faite pour être utile.
In rural India, girls are generally considered worthless.
En Inde rurale, les filles sont en général considérées comme sans valeur.
They're a liability or a burden. If they are considered useful, it is only to cook dishes, keep the house clean or raise children. As a second daughter of my conservative Indian family, I was fairly clear from a very early age that no one expected anything from me. I was conditioned to believe that the three identities that defined me -- poor village girl -- meant that I was to live a life of no voice and no choice.
Elles sont soit une responsabilité, soit un fardeau. Elles sont seulement utiles quand il s'agit de cuisiner, de nettoyer la maison ou d'élever les enfants. En étant la deuxième fille dans ma famille indienne conservatrice, je me suis rendu compte dès mon plus jeune âge que personne n'attendait rien de moi. J'étais conditionnée à croire que les trois identités qui me définissaient - pauvre fille villageoise - signifiaient que je devais vivre une vie sans voix, ni choix.
These three identities forced me to think that I should never have been born. Yet, I was. All throughout my childhood, as I rolled bidis alongside my mother, I would wonder: What did my future hold? I often asked my mother, with a lot of anxiety, "Amma, will my life be different from yours? Will I have a chance to choose my life? Will I go to college?" And she would reply back, "Try to finish high school first." I am sure my mother did not mean to discourage me. She only wanted me to understand that my dreams might be too big for a girl in my village. When I was 13, I found the autobiography of Helen Keller. Helen became my inspiration. I admired her indomitable spirit. I wanted to have a college degree like her, so I fought with my father and my relatives to be sent to college, and it worked. During my final year of my undergraduate degree, I desperately wanted to escape from being forced into marriage, so I applied to a fellowship program in Delhi, which is about 1,600 miles away from my village. (Laughter) In fact, I recall that the only way I could fill out the application was during my commute to college. I did not have access to computers, so I had to borrow a college junior's cell phone. As a woman, I could not be seen with a cell phone, so I used to huddle his phone under my shawl and type as slowly as possible to ensure that I would not be heard. After many rounds of interviews, I got into the fellowship program with a full scholarship. My father was confused, my mother was worried -- (Applause) My father was confused, my mother was worried, but I felt butterflies in my stomach because I was going to step out of my village
Ces trois identités m'ont fait penser que je n'aurais jamais dû naître. Pourtant, je le suis. Durant toute mon enfance, alors que je roulais des bidis avec ma mère, je me demandais : que me réserve l'avenir ? Je demandais souvent à ma mère, avec beaucoup d'angoisse : « Amma, ma vie sera-t-elle différente de la tienne ? Est-ce que j'aurai la chance de choisir ma vie ? D'aller à l'université ? » Elle me répondait : « Finis d'abord le lycée. » Je suis sûre que ma mère n'avait aucune intention de me décourager. Elle voulait juste que je comprenne que mes rêves étaient peut-être trop grands pour une fille de mon village. Quand j'avais 13 ans, j'ai trouvé une autobiographie d'Helen Keller. Helen est devenue mon inspiration. J'admirais son esprit indomptable. Je voulais avoir un diplôme universitaire comme elle, j'ai donc affronté mon père et mes proches pour qu'on m'envoie à l'université, et ça a marché. La dernière année du premier cycle, je voulais désespérément échapper au mariage forcé, j'ai donc postulé à un programme de bourse à Delhi, à environ 2 500 km de mon village. (Rires) En fait, je me souviens que le seul moyen était de remplir ma demande pendant mon trajet vers la fac. Je n'avais pas accès aux ordinateurs, j'ai donc dû emprunter le portable d'un camarade. En tant que femme, je n'avais pas le droit d'être vue avec un portable, je cachais alors son téléphone sous mon châle et je tapais le plus lentement possible pour ne pas être entendue. Après plusieurs entretiens, j'ai été acceptée dans le programme avec une bourse complète. Mon père était perturbé, ma mère était inquiète -- (Applaudissements) Mon père était perturbé, ma mère était inquiète, mais j'avais des papillons dans le ventre parce que j'allais quitter mon village
for the first time to study in the national capital. Of the 97 fellows selected that year, I was the only rural college graduate. There was no one there who looked like me or spoke like me. I felt alienated, intimidated and judged by many. One fellow called me "Coconut Girl." Can you guess why? Anyone? That's because I applied a lot of coconut oil to my hair. (Laughter) Another asked me where I had learned to speak English, and some of my peers did not prefer to have me on their assignment teams because they thought I would not be able to contribute to their discussion. I felt that many of my peers believed that a person from rural India could not supply anything of value, yet the majority of Indian population today is rural. I realized that stories like mine were considered to be an exception and never the expectation. I believe that all of us are born into a reality that we blindly accept until something awakens us and a new world opens up. When I saw my mother's first signature on her bidi-rolling wage book, when I felt the hot Delhi air against my face after a 50-hour train journey, when I finally felt free and let myself be, I saw a glimpse of that new world I longed for, a world where a girl like me is no longer a liability or a burden but a person of use, a person of value and a person of worthiness. By the time my fellowship ended, my life had changed. Not only had I traced my lost voice, but also had a choice to make myself useful. I was 22. I came back to my village to set up the Bodhi Tree Foundation, an institution that supports rural youth by providing them with education, life skills and opportunities. We work closely with our rural youth to change their life and to benefit our communities. How do I know my institution is working? Well, six months ago, we had a new joinee. Her name is Kaviarasi. I first spotted her in a local college in Tirunelveli during one of my training sessions. As you can see, she has a smile which you can never forget. We guided her to get an opportunity to study at Ashoka University, Delhi. The best part of her story is that she is now back at Bodhi Tree as a trainer working with dedication to make a change in the lives of others like her. Kaviarasi doesn't want to feel like an exception. She wants to be of use to others in this world. Recently, Kaviarasi mentored Anitha, who also comes from a remote, rural village, lives in a 10-foot-by-10-foot home, her parents are also farm laborers. Kaviarasi helped Anitha secure admission in a prestigious undergraduate program in a top university in India with a full scholarship. When Anitha's parents were reluctant to send her that far, we asked the district administration officials to speak to Anitha's parents, and it worked. And then there is Padma. Padma and I went to college together.
pour la première fois pour aller étudier dans la capitale. Parmi les 97 boursiers de cette année-là, j'étais la seule jeune diplômée issue du milieu rural. Personne d'autre ne me ressemblait, ni ne parlait comme moi. Je me sentais isolée, intimidée et jugée par beaucoup. Un camarade m'appelait « Coconut Girl ». Qui peut deviner pourquoi ? Personne ? Parce que j'utilisais beaucoup d'huile de coco dans mes cheveux. (Rires) Un autre m'a demandé comment j'avais appris l'anglais, et certains ne voulaient pas de moi dans leur groupe de travail parce qu'ils pensaient que je n'étais pas capable de contribuer à la discussion. J'ai senti que beaucoup de mes camarades pensaient qu'une personne de l'Inde rurale ne pouvait rien apporter de valeur, alors que la majorité de la population indienne est rurale. Une histoire comme la mienne est considérée comme une exception, et jamais comme une possibilité. Je crois qu'on naît tous dans une réalité qu'on accepte aveuglément, jusqu'à ce qu'on se réveille et qu'un nouveau monde s'ouvre. Quand j'ai vu la première signature de ma mère sur son carnet de salaire, quand j'ai senti l'air chaud de Delhi sur mon visage après un trajet de 50 heures en train, quand je me suis enfin sentie libre et moi-même, j'ai eu un aperçu de ce nouveau monde que je désirais, un monde dans lequel une fille comme moi n'est plus un fardeau, mais une personne de valeur, utile et une personne de mérite. À la fin de ma bourse, ma vie avait changé. J'avais non seulement retrouvé ma voix, mais j'avais aussi le choix de me rendre utile. J'avais 22 ans. Je suis retournée dans mon village pour créer la fondation Bodhi Tree, une institution qui soutient la jeunesse rurale en leur donnant une éducation, des compétences et des opportunités. On travaille avec les jeunes pour changer leur vie et aider nos communautés. Comment savoir que mon institution fonctionne ? Il y a six mois, une nouvelle personne nous a rejoints. Elle s'appelle Kaviarasi. Je l'ai repérée à l'université locale de Tirunelveli pendant l'une de mes séances de formation. On peut voir qu'elle a un sourire remarquable. On l'a aidée à aller étudier à l'université d'Ashoka, à Delhi. Le meilleur, c'est qu'elle est de retour à Bodhi Tree en tant que formatrice travaillant avec dévouement à changer la vie d'autres comme elle. Kaviarasi ne veut pas avoir l'impression d'être une exception. Elle veut être utile aux autres dans ce monde. Récemment, Kaviarasi a guidé Anitha, qui vient aussi d'un village reculé, vit dans une maison de neuf m², ses parents sont aussi ouvriers agricoles. Kaviarasi a aidé Anitha à intégrer un prestigieux programme dans une grande fac indienne avec une bourse complète. Devant la réticence de ses parents à l'envoyer aussi loin, on a demandé aux membres du comité de district de parler aux parents d'Anitha, et ça a marché. Et il y a Padma. Nous sommes allées à la fac ensemble.
She's the first in her entire village to attend graduation. She had been working with me at Bodhi Tree until one day she decides to go to graduate school. I asked her why. She told me that she wanted to make sure that she would never be a liability or a burden to anyone at any point in her life. Padma, Anitha and Kaviarasi grew up in the most tough families and communities one could only imagine. Yet the journey of finding my usefulness in this world served them in finding their usefulness to this world. Of course there are challenges. I'm aware change does not happen overnight. A lot of my work involves working with families and communities to help them understand why getting an education is useful for everyone. The quickest way to convince them is by doing. When they see their kids getting a real education, getting a real job, they begin to change. The best example is what happened at my home. I was recently given an award in recognition of my social work by the chief minister of my state. That meant I was going to be on television. (Laughter) Everyone was hooked on to the television that morning, including my parents. I would like to believe that seeing her daughter on television made my mother feel useful too. Hopefully, she will stop pressuring me to get married now. (Laughter) Finding my use has helped me to break free from the identities society thrusts on me -- poor village girl. Finding my use has helped me to break free from being boxed, caged and bottled. Finding my use has helped me to find my voice, my self-worth and my freedom. I leave you with this thought: Where do you feel useful to this world? Because the answer to that question is where you will find your voice and your freedom. Thank you. (Applause)
Elle est la première diplômée de son village. Elle travaillait avec moi à Bodhi Tree jusqu'à ce qu'elle décide d'aller à l'école supérieure. Je lui ai demandé pourquoi. Elle a dit qu'elle voulait s'assurer ne jamais être un fardeau pour qui que ce soit à aucun moment de sa vie. Padma, Anitha et Kaviarasi ont grandi dans les communautés et familles les plus difficiles qu'on puisse imaginer. Mais ma quête d'utilité dans ce monde leur a servi à trouver leur utilité pour ce monde. Bien sûr, il y a des défis. Je sais que le changement n'arrive pas soudainement. Je travaille beaucoup avec les familles et communautés pour les aider à comprendre pourquoi l'éducation est utile à tous. Agir permet de les convaincre rapidement. Quand ils voient leurs enfants s'instruire, avoir un vrai travail, ils commencent à changer. Ce qui s'est passé chez moi en est un bon exemple. J'ai reçu une récompense pour mon travail social du Ministre en chef de l'État. J'allais donc passer à la télévision. (Rires) Tout le monde était collé à la télé, y compris mes parents. Je voudrais croire que voir sa fille à la télé a aussi permis à ma mère de se sentir utile. Espérons maintenant qu'elle arrête de me forcer à me marier. (Rires) Trouver mon utilité m'a aidée à me libérer des identités imposées par la société -- pauvre fille villageoise. Trouver mon utilité m'a permis de ne pas être mise en boîte, en cage et en bouteille. Trouver mon utilité m'a aidée à trouver ma voix, ma propre estime et ma liberté. Je vous laisse avec cette réflexion : où vous sentez-vous utile à ce monde ? Dans la réponse à cette question, vous trouverez votre voix et votre liberté. Merci. (Applaudissements)